When opening the Buddha's name, the four Shakyamuni Buddhas, the four Shakyamuni
khi mở mô phật bốn thích ca mô bốn thích
Buddhas, Namo Buddha, the four Shakyamuni Buddhas, both wings
ca mô Nam Mô Phật bốn thích cả hai cánh
follow the orbit of friendship. Each of us
theo quỹ đạo hữu mỗi con người chúng ta
has a most important part,
có một cái phần quan trọng nhất nhé
which is finding a friend for ourselves. It's very self-centered. Have you ever spent your
ở đó là tìm người bạn cho chính mình rất
whole life searching for a
là từ có thấy cả cuộc đời đi tìm người
friend like yourself,
bạn như chính mình không
Ms. Ha? When we were little, we had friends in kindergarten, then
chị Hà lúc bé thì có bạn là mẫu giáo nhá
in middle school, then in high school, then in high school, then in
cấp 3 thì bạn ở cấp 3 nhá sau này trưởng
college, then colleagues, then life
thành rồi thì có bạn đại học nhé Rồi bạn
partners. After summer, we have friends, and then all
đồng nghiệp nhé Rồi bạn đời hè chấm dứt
kinds of friends. What else do we do?
thép các loại bạn chưa Thế làm gì nữa
Usually, we often
thấy và Thường thường chúng ta thường
feel attached to our friends. We organize
lưu luyến trên chúng ta tổ chức gặp mặt
reunions with
các bạn cấp 3 phải không tổ chức gặp mặt
high school friends, right? We organize reunions with university friends,
các bạn đại học tổ chức gặp mặt các bạn
reunions with classmates, reunions with friends from our hometown, reunions with colleagues,
đồng hương về tổ chức các bạn đồng
right? We
nghiệp đúng không gặp mặt các bạn đồng
organize reunions with colleagues and celebrate wedding anniversaries with life
nghiệp và tổ chức kỷ niệm ngày cưới là
partners. The element in
bạn đời trên cái yếu tố ở trong tâm
our hearts is the constant desire to find
chúng ta là khao khát luôn tìm
a friend, and
a cho mình một người bạn thì người bạn
that friend is the friend in our hearts, as long as that friend
đó là người bạn trong tâm của mình miễn
satisfies our hearts.
mình đã được thỏa mãn
Is it that I don't know how to use it? Now, if I have a
có phải không biết dùng Bây giờ tôi có
lover, and we've just started dating, I
người yêu thì vừa mới yêu nhau thì tôi
'll immediately leave them. At that age, playing around with
sẽ bỏ ngay trông bạn thân cái tuổi chơi
lovers, is there a factor that we
người yêu thế có yếu tố là do mình để
let our minds wander? If we let our
cho ông tâm thì không có bạn đâu không
minds wander, we won't have friends. Yes, this is true, isn't it? Always searching for a
luôn đi tìm cho cái tâm mình có một
friend for our minds, and a friend who
người bạn và cái người bạn nào mà làm
makes our minds suffer...
cho tâm mình đau khổ
Yes, if we feel suffering, we feel
Ừ thì mình cảm thấy khổ mình cảm chết
that friend is not good. But if a friend
người bạn đó không tốt còn người bạn nào
truly makes our minds comfortable,
đó thật cả làm cho tâm mình thoải mái
then we consider that a friend is good.
thì mình nhận xét đó là người bạn tốt
Yes, so is there a time when
Ừ thế thì có một lúc nào đó mà các quý
we, as Buddhist practitioners, clearly see that our minds are
phật tử chúng ta thấy rõ rằng tâm mình
sad, not
buồn không có không
happy?
em có rõ thấy là tâm mình vui không
And is there a time when we, as Buddhist practitioners, sit and
a và có lúc nào mà phật tử mình ngồi
observe that we don't want
quán sát lại là mình không muốn cái tấm
this mind to be sad or angry at others, not to be angry at others, not to be able to
này buồn giận người khác không có không
monitor that
có thịt cái gì mà để theo dõi được cả
mind?
cái tâm đấy ạ
Now, we keep analyzing
ạ Bây giờ chúng ta giữ Phân tích những
these minds, saying, "My mind, my mind,
giữ tâm này cứ nói là tâm tôi tâm tôi
my mind sees," but if my mind
tâm tôi thấy nhưng mà nếu mà tâm của tôi
doesn't want it, it still exists, it can't be gotten rid of.
thì tôi không muốn nó nó vẫn có không bỏ
I don't want the mind...
đi được chứ không Tôi không muốn cái tâm
Sadness, but it just stays sad. Isn't it true that sometimes
nỗi buồn nhưng nó cứ buồn Có phải có lúc
we want to get rid of it?
mình muốn bỏ nó đi không
But we can't just
anh đúng không nhưng chúng ta không thể
abandon our hearts; we
bỏ được tâm mình đi được mà chúng ta
have to transform them. For example, what you
phải chuyển hóa nó thôi ví dụ cái anh
see in Yen, you just call it what you see and know about
thấy Yến cứ gọi là cái anh thấy biết đến
it. Today, many young people see
nó vì hôm nay có nhiều bạn trẻ mà thấy
their hearts as sad, and it's because someone sees them, right?
cái tâm mình buồn thì là do ai thấy mình
We know our hearts are
thấy phải không Mình biết cái tên mình
sad, and we don't want to be sad, but it still stays
buồn và mình không muốn buồn mà nó vẫn
sad, right? We're still sad because we're afraid of
cứ buồn phải không vẫn buồn vì sợ cái
this sadness. But who is sad? It's the heart that's harming us. We see sadness, we
buồn này lắm thế nhưng mà ai buồn hại là
don't see it, we see it, we see it, we see it, we
cái tấm nỗi buồn thấy không họ hàng mà
hear it over and over again, and
sẻ của đạo hữu thế này đạo hữu về nghe
it still stays sad. We can't
đi nghe lại nó vẫn cứ buồn không thể nào
do anything about it. We keep going back and forth, and the sadness still lingers.
làm khác được chạy đi chạy lại vẫn có
For example, this friend of mine,
buồn Ví dụ như hạt tức cái người bạn này
for instance,
chẳng hạn
when I open my eyes and don't want to be angry anymore, I want to go and make
khi mở không muốn tức nữa muốn đến làm
amends, but my heart prevents me from going. I stay
lành mà cái tâm nó ngăn cản mình không
home, think carefully, and say, '
đến được không ở nhà suy nghĩ kỹ rồi Hôm
Today I will stop.' I'm tired of you, I'm not
nay ta sẽ thôi không đã chán bạn không
sad, you come and say this and
buồn bạn đến lại nói bạn thế này nói bạn
that to me, but seeing your face makes me
thế kia nhưng mà nhìn thấy mặt nó đã
furious, and then I make you furious again,
điên tiết rồi lại cho tập nó điên tiết
unable to say a word. I'll never get
lên không nói được câu ký đồ hiệu không
into school.  Is that situation not the case? Has
bao giờ bị vào trường hợp đó không
anyone who is married experienced
Có ai có chồng có vợ rồi có bị trường
this? Especially with you and your wife,
hợp đó không Nhất là với chị cùng với vợ
right? Thinking about this husband is so
đúng không nghĩ đến cái anh chồng này
infuriating. Today he went out
điên tiếp lắm là hôm nay anh ấy đi là
past the scheduled time and didn't even bother to call home, right? I
quá giờ không thèm gọi điện về đúng
sat and thought for a while, then I had to
không cho ngồi suy nghĩ một lúc tí về
give him a picture, this wasn't like
phải trả ảnh cho cái này chẳng như thế
this, and then I thought about it, and we argued, and I said, "
này xong rồi nghĩ rằng trỏ như thế lại
Okay, no
cãi nhau cãi nhau bảo thôi không Khoảng
more." But then when I got home and saw his face, I was
nữa nhưng mà tí về nhìn thấy mặt lại
shocked, not like this anymore. When
choáng không phải này nữa ra khi thằng
Tâm was shocked, he was like Mr. Quý Đạo Hữu Thức, and
Tâm nó choáng phải ông Quý Đạo Hữu Thức
then he went out. You went on a date,
rồi chồng đi Bạn đi hẹn không người ta
but you missed the date, and you
ngỡ hẹn thì anh lỡ hẹn tâm mình bực tức
broke the date. Tâm was angry and said, "Where did you see that friend?" He didn't know, only his own heart was suffering, wasn't it? It was very painful, wasn't it? Two feet up is the factor of Tâm, he's always affected by external circumstances. Today, I'm just talking about a
ngoài đi hôm nay nhấn chỉ nói một cái
simple aspect, not much, just about
mặt đơn giản thôi không nói nhiều nói về
you.
bạn thôi nhé
When talking about money or anything, I'm not
Khi nói đến tiền tài của cái gì Không
talking about it, only about one aspect: you. I've
nói đến mà chỉ nói một khía cạnh là bạn
established my heart, it's always
Em lập cái tâm của mình nó luôn luôn có
directed towards finding a friend,
hướng tới tìm cho nó một người bạn không
it never stands still alone. That's it.
lúc nào nó chịu đứng yên một mình đấy là
Laypeople, as for those who come out today,
cư sĩ tại gia còn người xuất ra hôm nay
let's not talk about that Dharma, but
không nói đến pháp đó nhé nhưng người cư
laypeople always seek out their
sĩ tại gia luôn luôn tìm đến cho người
friends, for example, if they're angry with their husband, a
bạn ví dụ như là đang bực chồng chẳng
friend might call and ask, "Do you like it?
hạn có bạn với bạn nó gọi đến có thích
Do you like it? I like it so much!" They say, "Hello,"
không thích không thích quá đi chứ Alo
without knowing the other person's feelings, "I'll tell you my story first." Then, the heart, filled with emotion, speaks up, "I don't
Tâm mất đầy cảm xúc nó nói ra tôi không
know if the other person will listen, right?"
biết người ta có nghe không nữa đúng
Then, the
không kể chuyện kể chuyện thế rồi cái
heart wants to be soothed. For example, if
tâm nó lại muốn vuốt ve cái ví dụ như là
a friend says, "You're wrong, that's your fault," does
cái người bạn cái nói mày sai là do rồi
the heart like it? If the friend says, "Yes,
thì cái tâm nó có thích không Nó bảo ừ
that guy was wrong," the heart likes it.
cái thằng kia sai rồi Tâm thích cho
The heart responds with a dramatic, dramatic tone, wanting to
xe tải kịch Tấm nói lại một lòng muốn
be soothed, to be
được vuốt ve làm cho nó được thỏa mãn
satisfied. That's why the heart ca
ý chính vì thế cho nên cái tâm không tự
n't orient itself.
định hướng được mà không định hướng được
Firstly, it needs something similar. Secondly, the heart
thứ nhất là nó cần có lấy tương tự thứ
wants to be soothed, so the heart
hai Long muốn vuốt ve cho nên là cái tâm
can't orient itself. It just wants someone who has a similar
nó tự không định hướng được cứ ai có
nature to it. That is, whoever
tính chất làm cho nó lương tự Tức là nó
connects with it, it will connect with them. Whoever
kết nối mình thì mình sẽ kết với nó Ai
has a soothing nature, it will rely
có tính vuốt ve nó thì nó sẽ nương tựa
on.  That's why we have
vào người đó cho nên mới có những cái
cases where people associate with bad friends,
trường hợp con người chơi với bạn xấu
people do evil things.
con người làm có việc bất thiện đấy trên
We must recognize this in time. The mind
chúng ta phải nhận diện ra kịp Tâm ở
within us has
trong chỗ chúng ta nó có cái điểm yếu
its weaknesses; it has two weaknesses: firstly,
của nó là gì nó có hai điểm yếu thứ nhất
it needs support, and secondly, it needs
là nó cần nương tựa thứ hai nó cần vuốt
comforting. If we can see and understand
ve trên nếu như cái Và mình thấy biết
this, as I just mentioned today, I want to clarify this
được nó đấy vừa nãy hôm nay đến nói có
for you all. I see
cái này cho các quỹ đạo hữu rõ mình thấy
it's sad, I see the mind is sad, and
nó buồn thấy cái tâm nó buồn thì cái
this is what we
thấy này
call our intellect.
A gọi là trí của chúng ta đấy nhá thích
Our intellect must be clear and discerning,
trí của chúng ta nó phải sáng suốt cho
knowing that the mind is like that. We
biết là cái thằng tâm như thế Mình định
guide it to find a friend
hướng cho nó phải tìm cái người bạn nào
to rely on, something to comfort it—those
để nương tựa lấy cái gì để vuốt ve nó
two things. We must have them; if we do
hai cái ô tô đấy Mình phải có nếu không
n't, in life we ​​easily fall into temptation, easily
có thì trong cuộc đời mình dễ sa ngã dễ
fail, and often encounter suffering.
thất bại và hay gặp đau khổ
Perhaps we should find
Có thể chúng ta phải tìm cho nó những
good friends for it to reward it. (Image of a
người bạn làng thiện để cho nó lương
profile picture, do you see it correctly?) So that when
ảnh đại diện có thấy đúng không để khi
it has a problem, it doesn't go looking for
mà nó có cái vấn đề gì nóng dao đi tìm
that "mind," and it loses
cái thằng cái thằng Trí rồi nó không
control. It doesn't call, it doesn't
kiểm soát rồi đó đâu gọi điện không gọi
call, it doesn't call, but it
điện gọi điện không gọi điện nhưng nó
still...  That's what you call it. Tâm is
bất tên là vẫn gọi thế cái thằng Tâm nó
slow, he's won against Trí, right? The
chậm Thắng thằng Trí rồi phải không
key is, for example, he feels very hungry, very
tuyến chìa khóa ví dụ thấy bụng rất là
hungry. There's something
đói Đói lắm đấy có một cái món gì đó lắm
he wants to cook, and he wants to hire someone to
mình nấu ăn mà tí mình bảo thuê thì mình
cook it for him, so he can bring it back to Thu Hương.
để mình nấu ăn mình mang về Thu Hương đã
But he's very hungry, so he's taking a break.
nhưng mà đói lắm rồi thải lao cái thằng
Trí says no, it's for
Trí thì nó bảo không được tên như là để
offering incense, not for eating. Then
thắp hương đã không được ăn Thế thằng
Tâm is craving it, so he takes control.
tâm thì nó thèm thèm thế là nó làm chủ
Trí says, "Just
luôn cái thằng Trí nó bảo cái thằng Trí
put a little bit on the plate,
là một gắp ra đĩa một tí một ấy còn bớt
leave a little bit for the bowl, okay?"
lại một tí ở xong để chén có không thế
Tâm thinks, "Comrade, have you figured it out yet?"
Thằng Tâm nó suy được đồng chí chưa ạ
After Tâm immediately places his order,
sau khi đặt ngay của cái thằng Tâm đấy
he's very formidable in his cooking. He says that so that
Nó rất là ghê gớm chế biến nói thế để
we Buddhists can be close to the restaurant,
cho Phật tử chúng ta gần gũi là quán xá
so that we can take control of the
được nó để chúng ta lấy cái chí làm chủ
truth. Otherwise, what would we
cái thật chứ nếu không chúng ta làm gì
know? If he needs a friend and we
biết đâu Nếu như mà nó cần một người bạn
don't give him one, he'll go
mình không cho nó người bạn thì nó sẽ đi
looking around and take control of the main thing, right? He wo
tìm lung tung và nó làm chủ cái chính ai
n't be in control anymore. He
phải không đâu có làm chủ nó nữa đâu nó
'll say, "Okay, this time offering incense is enough."
lại bảo là thôi lần này thắp hương đủ
And this is forbidden to eat. If you can't control him, you'll
rồi Còn cái này là cấm ăn đi được chí là
lose. So we know.  With that kind of
thua luôn hãy cho nên mình biết sẵn cái
mental state, I'll find
yếu tố của tâm như vậy mình tìm cho nó
a friend for it. And I haven't mentioned a
một người bạn Và mình tìm chưa nói một
method to help it go yet. You're a
phương pháp để nó đi nhé Thì bạn là bạn
spiritual friend, the method is observing karma,
đạo phương pháp là quán sát nhân quả
right? So I'll force both Tri and
anh đúng không Thì mình ép cả anh Trí và
Tam to follow that. Gradually, it will go away.
anh Tâm theo điều đó Dần dần nó sẽ ra đi
Gradually, Tri will be able to guide
được dần dần cái thằng Trí sẽ bảo được
Tam, and I will achieve happiness.
thằng Tâm và mình sẽ có được hạnh phục à
For example, today, Ms. Huyen is suffering from karmic retribution
Thì nói ví dụ hôm nay chị Huyền chẳng ạ
from past lives.
và bị bị nghiệp báo trong các tiền kiếp
For instance, she had the karma of being unfilial.
nào đó ví dụ chị có cái nghiệp bất hiếu
Today, it's paying the price because her
Thế hôm nay nó mới nó mới đi báo hiệp là
boyfriend is infatuated with someone who
đứa bạn trai lại thích ngay phải một đứa
lacks morality. He goes home and immediately
nó đạo đức nó không ra vì nó về nhà nó
introduces him as his lover.
giới thiệu luôn ở đây là người yêu con
Ms. Huyen then examines him,
thế thì có đầu chị Huyền mới xem xét xem
seeing what he's like, noticing only bad things about him, and nothing
là thứ đi vô nó thế nào thấy cái gì của
good at all. She just
nó cũng dở ông cái gì là tốt cả ngày
says, "Let's all
không đấy thì cứ nói để cho đại chúng
see his face. I don't see
chúng ta xem mặt tao cũng ở không thấy
anything good either." She doesn't ask about the movement.
mặt nào tốt đi không hỏi về phong trào
The karma of Vinh from before will be
cái là cái nghiệp của Vĩnh lúc trước sẽ
suspended, and he'll have a filial child. Let's try
đình chỉ sinh được con có hiếu mình thử
that. That's the Phuc Chien method. Now,
cái đấy thôi Phúc chiến đấy thôi bây giờ
with experience, it's lacking, it will flow smoothly.
à
Minh lost his girlfriend, brought his
đã nó bị rớt một đứa người yêu Minh đưa
unfilial wife home, and then they conspired to make
vợ bất hiếu về rồi nó xui nhau lắm bắt
us suffer. It's karma, isn't it?
chúng mình chứ cái nghiệp phải không còn
Before, it was like, for example, in a
lúc trước thì lại ví dụ như là kiếp
previous life, we created three parts of merit. I told you to create
trước ta tạo ra 3 phần Phước Tao bảo tạo
good karma. Now, we have the opportunity to
các bài thật nghiệp bây giờ có cái duyên
live near several people with good fortune, and we've
sống được gần mấy người có phước mình
enjoyed it all. In the process of
được hưởng cho hết rồi trong quá trình
enjoying that merit, we didn't create
hưởng phước Thế thì mình lại không tạo
the karmic causes of loyalty and filial piety. We only
những cái nhân chung nghĩa Hiếu mình chỉ
ate up the old karmic debt. Now, we've
ăn cục cái cũ đi thôi Đến bây giờ mình
run out of it, and now our son has turned on the
hết rồi thịt đến duyên thằng con mình nó
idea and brought home an unfilial wife,
bật hiệu với về cho nó rước một đứa bất
right? So, at what point?
hiếu phải đúng không Thế đến lúc mấy giờ
Why is the heart so upset?
Sao cái Tâm có bức xúc không
Because he says, "My son is my child." Now, my son is
à Vì nói con trai là con Bây giờ con con
like this... Oh no, Mom, help me, Mom, where are you going? You're so uncaring, and
như thế Ui rồi Mẹ Đỡ Mẹ đi đâu vật rồi
you're not even showing compassion and forgiveness. If he
mà mẹ không Từ bi hỷ xả thì xinh mà nó
says that, it's precious, right? If
nói như thế cho quý lời đúng không ạ Nếu
he doesn't... If he doesn't... If he uses the medicine, and he
nó không Nếu mà kích cái thuốc của mình
still has a filial son, he'll say, "That's right,
còn có con có hiếu thì nó bảo ở Đúng rồi
Mom, if you don't say anything, I won't see it,
đấy Mẹ mẹ không nói thì con không nhìn
right?" "I won't see it, okay,
ra đúng không Không nhìn ra thôi được
I'll teach him
rồi đả cái đấy thì con sẽ bảo nó dậy nó
gradually." If we consider the medicine
dần dần đây Nếu như mình coi cái thuốc
weak, then our son will behave like that, but
và yếu thì con mình sẽ ứng xử thế nhưng
we...  The minute hand went to the bank, and I spent all my money. Then
mà mình kim phút về hiếu mình tiêu hết
he said, "Mom, come up here and
rồi thì nó bảo Mẹ lên tất nhập từ từ bi
pay me back slowly." Suddenly, Mom went to jail for
trả cho tôi bỗng chốc lát mẹ đi tù của
that stuff?
chất đấy à
Yeah, what? It turns out he even demanded to be
Ừ cái gì hóa ra là nó lại còn đòi nó to
taller than me?
cao hơn cả mình à
He said that, but my son hasn't... So at
anh bảo thế mà con mình chưa Thế thì lúc
that time, the factor is that I have to find a
bấy giờ là yếu tố là mình phải tìm với
friend with a clear understanding of the wind, my son is no
người bạn có gió rõ con không làm bạn
longer a friend. Now, do I have to find a friend,
nữa rồi giờ có phải đi tìm bạn không
right? Find a friend who doesn't know about
đúng không tìm một cái bạn không biết về
cause and effect, not a friend of the right path, right?
nhân về quả không phải bạn đạo chứ gì mà
At first, that friend just brings bad luck. Now I say, "Leave that
ban đầu bạn hay xui thôi Bây giờ tôi bảo
guy." Now, if we're like this, we
Bỏ thằng đấy chúc Bây giờ mình như thế
'll bring a bull to trample on our ancestors' graves. That's
thì về rước voi về giày mả tổ Thế là
death. Now the real danger is that he has
chết đấy Bây giờ mới là nguy cơ mà nó
n't even become my daughter-in-law yet, and he's already figured out
chưa về làm con dâu mình mà nó đã đã suy
my son's nature. At least a
được con trai mình như thế thì ít nữa
few more times, you'll die. So, Mom,
vài là mày chết Thế không thế là mẹ về
why would you come back and cause discord with your son?
sao gây bất hòa với con ra phải không
So, the daughter-in-law won't have a son, and you'll
Thế là con dâu đã chả có con trai lại
lose him too, right? So, the two of us will
mất luôn đúng không Thế là hai mẹ con cứ
fight fiercely. He loves that girl
kịch liệt với nhau nó thì nó yêu con bé
because of his experiment. Now, after
lại cơ bởi thí nghiệm của nó mà đã yêu
I finish beating him up, I'll go
con bé này có thế Giờ mình đánh xong lên
quickly so he'll leave, and then he'll hate me.  You're
nhanh này cho nó bỏ thì nó ghét mày
letting her go, she won't love anyone anymore,
buông tuồng nó không yêu ai nữa
right? But clearly, we have
anh đúng không Mà rõ ràng mình có cái
karma. No matter what, she'll always find
nghiệp Có thiếu gì nó tìm đâu cũng phải
someone quick with her left hand to grab and bring home. She
cái đứa nhanh tay trái bắt mang về nó
only likes the cool, left-handed approach. And
chỉ ưa Cái hướng tay trái mát thôi còn
Vinh, my friend, has a guy named Hiep Quoc, and
Vinh thiệp của mình có thằng Hiệp Quốc
his daughter-in-law understands. If you say you love someone 10 times, then 10 times it's someone who's unlucky, right? We haven't changed our karma, so why demand that our fate change? Now it's about the
của mình đã thay đổi thế bây giờ là kỷ
mental factor. We give her a
yếu tố tâm của mình à mình cho nó người
spiritual friend. Then when we share with that spiritual
bạn đạo Rồi đến lúc mình chia sẻ người
friend, when it rains, the spiritual friend will say... That means
bạn đạo thì lúc mưa bạn đạo sẽ nói Tức
we have two factors: first, a
là mình có hai yếu tố thứ nhất là bạn
spiritual friend, and second, sharing with each other on the
đạo thứ hai là chia sẻ với nhau trên quả
karmic path. That's your
người bạn ạ Cái đấy là nhân quả của bạn
bad karma. It's best to be compassionate and forgiving.
không tốt rồi tốt hơn hết là bà Từ Bi và
You should befriend her and teach
hỷ xả bà cứ kết thân với nó rồi bà dạy
her gradually. That's how you change karma,
nó dần đấy là cái và chuyển nghiệp đấy
right? Then go do good deeds. Now,
đúng không Rồi bà đi làm phúc đi bây giờ
your blessings are decreasing, and you're suffering.
kia phúc của bà nó bị giảm bà với bị thế
You need to know how to make offerings, do good deeds, and cultivate merit
bà phải biết cúng giường làm phúc tu tập
to increase your blessings. She doesn't
về phước báo là tăng lên thì bà nó không
know, right? So, have I
biết đúng chưa Thế là tao giải quyết
resolved the mental factor yet? Our
được yếu tố của Tâm chưa chúng ta đau
suffering is due to...  We don't recognize
khổ là do chúng ta không nhận diện được
our own minds, but if we do recognize them,
cái tâm của mình còn chúng ta biết nhận
we know how to please them. Our minds
ta biết đường chiều nó chứ cái tấm của
don't beat up; we have to please them.
mình không đánh đập Nó được phải chiều
They appreciate and understand. But there must
nó đấy nó quý và hiểu Nhưng chiều phải
be a way to please them, right? We
có cách đúng không Mình phải viết chiều
have to write about how to please our minds. Actually, we can't
tâm mình có cách chức thực ra mình không
force them to be happy; they won't be happy
thể bắt ép đang vui bắt nó buồn nó có
if we make them sad. They won't be
buồn được đâu Đang buồn bắt nó vui nó có
happy if we make them happy if we make them happy. When they're happy, we have to do something about it, and
vui được đâu Đang vui thì phải làm sau
to limit it, we need a
đó để hạn chế nó thì phải có cái tư duy
mindset to limit it completely. To
suy nghĩ để hạn chế hết hạn chế được
limit it, we need a friend, a companion, to
phải có bạn đồng hữu cùng nhau hạn chế
limit it together. That's not right, we need a friend and a method. When they're sad, they won't be happy either. We need a friend, and that friend must give us a method. That's why we have a spiritual practice center that satisfies
chúng ta có đạo tràng tu tập thỏa mãn
us with those two elements: a friend
cho chúng ta hai yếu tố đó là người bạn
and a method. Perhaps that's the
và phương pháp Có khi nào yếu ông đấy là
benefit of practicing in a spiritual center.
lợi ích của việc tu tập trong đạo tràng
If our minds are always
nếu như cái tâm của mình nó luôn luôn
satisfied, we
em luôn luôn được thỏa mãn thì chúng ta
will go downhill because they lack
sẽ đi xuống dốc bởi vì nó không có định
direction.  You say, "You're right,
hướng cứ cái gì mà bảo là mày đúng rồi
you're so good, you're like this and that," and
đấy mày tốt lắm mày thế này thế kia thế
the mind likes it, right? But
là cái Tâm nó thích phải không Thế nhưng
we guide it to like it, following the law of cause and
mình định hướng cho nó là phải thích
effect, right? Gradually, will
thôi chiều nhân quả đúng không dần dần
it follow? It follows and goes
thế là nó có theo không nó theo mà đi
on. Just to give an example for those who
đến chỉ lấy ví dụ cho các quỹ đạo hữu
previously didn't know about Buddhism, didn't
trước kia chưa biết đến phật pháp chưa
know anything about cause and effect, and now they become more noble, creating
biết gì đến nhân quả thêm cao quý tạo
words outwardly. Hearing about the mother-in-law and
chữ ra ngoài Nghe thấy chuyện của mẹ
daughter-in-law relationship, we can
chồng nàng dâu nó như thế là mình có thể
participate freely, but
tham gia một cách thoải mái nhưng bây
now we listen, are we more reserved?
giờ mình nghe mình có dè dặt hơn không
Here, it's because our own cause and effect are
ở đây là do cái chính nhân quả của mình
beginning to transform and accumulate.
nó bắt đầu chuyển hóa được kết tập
Only those who have renounced worldly life
anh chỉ có những người xuất gia tu đạo
and become monks or nuns can stand still alone for a long time,
mà người ta phải cu lâu một thời gian
without needing friends around them. But it takes a
không cần người bạn xung quanh nhưng mà
very long time to achieve that, it's
phải vô lâu mới được như thế rất lâu chứ
not quick.
không phải là nhanh đâu có quỹ đạo hữu
Even with friends, one still needs to practice; without friends, one
còn vẫn phải có tu có bạn không có bạn
cannot resolve things because of the mental factor of the
không giải quyết được bởi bị yếu tố của
mind. From the beginning of the cycle of existence, one always relies
tâm là Từ Vô Thụy kiếp luôn nương tựa
on circumstances, but also on others.
vào cảnh nhưng tựa vào người khác rồi
Just to give an example, if there were no people,
khiến chỉ nói ví dụ không có người thì
it would be similar to relying on objects. For example, "I'm so sad."
nó tương tự vào vật Ví dụ Buồn quá đi 5
These five friends... I also...  A friend who
người bạn này cháu cũng người bạn nào
helps me relax by admiring flowers
làm cho mình khuây khỏa đi ngắm bông hoa
alone—isn't that still relying on something
một mình có phải là vẫn nương tựa gần
similar? It can't be alone. I
tương tự đấy chứ nó không ở một mình
have to understand the
được trên mình phải hiểu về kích khiếu
triggers of my own mind to be able to diligently cultivate
tố của tâm mình mới có thể tinh tấn mà
happiness. That means diligently
giúp cho mình được hạnh phúc đó là mình
associating with virtuous, knowledgeable, and spiritual friends.
tinh tấn thân cận bậc thiện lành tri
Yes, to help my mind grow and
Ừ để giúp trực tâm mình được tăng trưởng
to help me mold my mind.
để giúp cho mình uốn nắn được cái tâm
It's not about becoming a monk or helping
đạo mà đi giúp ai đâu nhá chẳng qua chỉ
others; it's simply a place of refuge. Before, those
là chỗ nương tựa để giúp mình trước đây
intelligent people were in a position of extreme self-importance,
là những người thông mình là chức cực
and my mind was
hình này khối chữ ích kỷ thì cái tâm của
n't taught by anyone. So now, I rely on
mình không có người dậy đâu thế bây giờ
spiritual friends. Listen to the song,
quỹ đạo hữu Xem luôn luôn nương tựa Nghe
do you like it? That's because my mind is
bài phá có thích không Đấy là do cái tâm
joyful and relies on the
nó hoan hỷ nương tựa vào các cái điều
most virtuous things. Only then can my intellect be
thiện lành nhất quả đấy thì cái trí của
satisfied. My mind
mình nó mới được thỏa mãn được tâm năm
listens, right? Like in a factory, if
anh nghe trí được đúng không Chứ nhà máy
one person is strong, another must lead
múc mà anh này mạnh thì anh kia phải dẫn
closely; if that person is strong, then this person must
rát lúc anh kia mạnh thì anh này phải
lead closely. For example, there are times when the
dẫn sát đấy ví dụ như lần những cái lúc
mind is very strong and then becomes sad and
mà tâm nó rất là Cường Thịnh rồi nó buồn
depressed.  If you can't do anything,
nó buồn bã mình không làm gì được thì
your mind can't solve it. You have to
cái trí của mình nó không giải quyết
let it reach a friend or someone with the right
được Phải cho nó đến người bạn
idea at that moment. You can't do anything anymore, you just can't work. There are
ý tưởng lúc bây giờ Chí có làm việc nữa
many
đâu chả làm gì được chứ em có nhiều
Buddhists who have practiced for a very
Những người phật tử tu một thời gian rất
long time but don't seek out
dài nhưng lại không chịu tìm cho mình
close friends or places of
những người bạn thân thiết những cái chỗ
refuge in Buddhism. They
nương tựa trong Phật pháp tự một mình
haven't reached that point alone. Sometimes they get
mình chưa đến Có những lúc đấy họ tự
discouraged and stop practicing, becoming dissatisfied and
mình chán không tu giống như có bất mãn
doing things without any karmic consequences
nữa làm những cái việc không có nhân quả
because they lack support and
gì cả bởi vì thường không có chỗ nương
sharing. They're always alone, feeling like they're
tựa chia sẻ nó cứ một mình có quen đi có
surrounded by ghosts. When it's time to cultivate, they get bored. There's
quỷ đỏ Ruộng thì đến lúc quay là chán
no one to share with anymore. Some
quá Không có ai chia sẻ nữa đấy Có những
people, at first, even their friends in the outside world
người mới đầu tôi thì bạn ở ngoài đời
don't follow them anymore because they're
cũng không theo nữa bởi vì cái bạn đây
afraid of karma. But once they enter the religion, they
sợ nhân quả nhưng mà vào trong đạo thì
can't make friends with fellow
lại không kết thân được với những cái
practitioners, they can't be close to them, they ca
người bạn đạo không gần gũi được người
n't share
bạn đạo không chia sẻ được điều hay điều
good things with them. They just stay isolated, unwilling to
tốt đấy cứ thui thủi như thế không chịu
share, unwilling to help others.
chia sẻ không chịu ghi giúp đỡ người ta
Regarding these mental factors, helping
em về các yếu tố tâm này giúp được người
others makes the mind happy, right?
ta thì cái tâm nó sao nó vui đúng không
This is like when you were a child.  If my mother taught me how to
Đây giống như hồi bé đấy nếu mà mẹ mình
hold chopsticks, would I feel happy? It's not about
cầm được mình có thấy vui không cần một
showing off to others, but about
lúa rồi có khác cho người khác không thể
what kind of showing it is. It's about the
hiện mà cái thể hiện đấy là cái gì yếu
heart's desire to show off, right?
tố của Tâm nó thích thể hiện đúng không
Now, I'm giving it that showing off
trên mình Bây giờ mình đưa cái thể hiện
by letting it do
cho nó bằng cách mà cho mày đi làm việc
good deeds. You have to understand that heart, otherwise,
thiện được không phải hiểu tâm đấy chứ
if it just stays alone, it
nếu không cứ thui thủi một mình như vậy
won't want to help anyone. That's a
cũng không muốn làm hộ ai đấy là cái trí
clouded mind, it won't guide the heart. I
lông mù mờ nó không dẫn đổi cái tâm tôi
just don't understand that clouded mind, it can't
cứ nào hiệu cái trí lông mù mở nó không
guide the heart, so it just lets
dẫn được cái tâm thế thành ra là để cho
the heart see someone. It's like
cái Tâm nó có thu thủ nhìn thấy ai đó mà
creating a heart, but the heart is
thôi Được làm ra các anh Tâm đã anh Tâm
worthless, the mind is so clouded. And then you
không ra gì ghê trí lại mù mịt Thế lại
bring it to the heart? Come on, why
đem dẫn cho anh Tâm à Thôi nào làm gì
bother, why go help people? Then the
cho mệt tội gì đi giúp người ra thế là
heart won't come here, it'll stay
thằng Tâm nó không qua đây đi nó cũng ở
home, right? At some point, the
nhà đúng không thấy đến một lúc nào đó
heart feels
Cái thằng Tâm nó cảm thấy
lonely and sad, it won't listen to the
cô đơn và buồn tủi nó không nghe thằng
mind anymore. It feels too lonely, right?
Trí nữa Cảm thấy cô đơn quá đúng không
It won't listen to sincerity anymore, it prefers to
nó không nghe thành chí nữa nó thích đi
follow those street thugs,
theo cái Bọn bụi đời chứ cơ Cái bọn bất
those evil people, right?  Today, we came
thiện kia đúng không Hôm nay đến đến đến
to this place to eat and drink. For example, let's say we
đến cái chỗ này ăn uống Ví dụ nói là đi
followed the back-and-forth crowd, went out there,
theo bọn bụi thời đấy đi ra ngoài kia
saw three or five old friends, and Zozo
thấy năm ba đứa bạn cũ của mình nó Zozo
invited us in. The guy named Tam was
cái nó rủ vào đi vào đây cái thằng tâm
sad, so he went right away, right?
thì nó đang buồn thì nó đi ngay đúng
So, the next day, he thought it was fun, and
không zodi Vào đây Thế là hôm sau thấy
Tam told Chi and the others, "
hay hay thế là thằng Tâm nó lại bảo mấy
I'm going to hide, don't go!" He said, "Those
thằng Chí là tôi đi trốn đừng đi Nói mấy
guys are writing..." He secretly followed
cái bọn cái viết Cứ thế đi lén lút theo
them, and they had fun. The key factor is that Tam
cái bọn này nó vui thế kỷ yếu tố tâm nó
likes to have fun, so is
thích vui
n't that why we're at a disadvantage? That's why
vì thế mà mình có thiệt thòi không Thế
people come from Buddhism,
là người từ trong đạo Phật đi ra cho nên
so the Buddha taught us to give alms to make the mind
Đức Phật Mới dậy mà bố thí để cho Tâm nó
joyful. Isn't that still teaching us to give alms quickly? The
hoan hỷ đấy có phải là vẫn là dậy Cái ta
Buddha taught wisdom, but to make
mau bố thí là Phật dạy trí nhưng để cho
the mind joyful, that's what we should do. In the Buddhist community, we often look for things to give alms to each other, to soothe our minds with good deeds. Then,
bằng các việc gì việc thiện thì thằng
if we don't give alms, then we're
Trí mới bảo nó chứ nếu không thì không
failing. Throughout
bảo nó là mình thất bại đấy trên cả cuộc
our lives, we only suffer because of
đời của mình mình chỉ khổ mấy cái thằng
Tam. We suffer because of outsiders,
Tâm thôi nói là khổ với người ngoài chứ
not because of anything else.  It's painful for those with a "Heart" (or "Mind"), for example,
không phải đau khổ mấy thằng Tâm ví dụ
Yen is just giving an example to show how much suffering those with a "Heart"
Yến chỉ lấy ví dụ xem khổ mấy thằng Tâm
suffer. It's only when you see outsiders at a
mới khổ với người ngoài nhá trong một
dinner table that there's a big piece of food, but you
bàn ăn này có miếng to nhưng bé mà sẽ
're hungry, right? The big piece is for the other guy,
đang đói đúng không cái mới to thằng kia
then it's your turn, and then there are only the small pieces left. You like them,
các trước rồi đến lượt mình chỉ còn
but
những bé thôi thích nhưng mà đáng ra chỉ
you should only eat the small ones. It's just that you're destined to eat the small ones.
sẽ ăn uống bé là mình ăn những bé thôi
Yes, whatever calories they eat, they still have that
Ừ thì nó ăn bao nhiêu calo nó còn bấy
much left.
nhiêu thính nhưng mà vừa ăn những bé
But while eating the small pieces, your greedy heart says, "
nhưng cái tâm tham ăn nó bảo mẹ thằng
Mom, why are you so greedy? You eat without even
kia sao mày tham thế mẹ ăn mà không biết
looking at yourself!" Not only do you not know your calories, but you
nhìn mình đấy Cái này đã không biết calo
also add a checkered pants and get angry at
thì chớ lại còn thêm một cái quần caro
people. It's
về bực tức người ta được chứ có phải là
not like you're losing calories. To have a clear understanding of your own heart, it's only funny if you know what's going on. We keep saying, "Who's going to suffer?" It's our own heart that suffers, right? For example, two sisters-in-law are together,
không cái ví dụ như là hai chị lập được
like the older sister-in-law, who is being criticized and
cái dùng như là cái bà chị dâu chẳng hạn
badmouthed by the younger sister-in-law.
bị cái cô em dâu kích bác nói xấu xa cái
You know your heart is very
gì đó mình biết là cái tâm mình rất ở
upset, but because of
khó chịu rồi thế nhưng mà vì cái tông
your own nature...  It's so annoying, when
của mình nó khó chịu như thế thì khi
you expect your husband to hear about it from your sister-in-law, and then
mong chồng cũng đã nghe qua em dâu mà
hear about it from her, he might be angry with you, but it's
nghe kia thì về có thể thức với mình
unclear whether your mind is okay or not. If you do
không rõ rằng tức mới mình thì tâm mình
n't recognize your own mind,
ở chỗ này mà không nhận diện là cái tâm
you'll be deceived, right?
là mình sẽ bị mắc lừa nó đấy đúng không
It will lead you to a bad place. These two men are already
nó dẫn mình đi về chỗ xấu hai ông này nó
bad, and now it's your turn. He has
xấu rồi bây giờ đến lượt mình ông đã
n't come back, so he's already present, and
không về cái thì bắt đầu là ông ấy đủ có
everything is there, right?
mặt mình hết tất cả mọi thứ đấy đúng
Now, is your mind angry?
không Bây giờ cái tâm mình có tức không
Angry at the future wife? No
tức cô Tương Lai ông chồng không tương
future husband? The husband is over there, and those two
lai ông chồng thì đương kia bên kia hai
are allies. If you're in the
người nó là có đồng minh luôn tài mình
future, then of course you'll become even more
sẽ tương lại thì đương nhiên là mình lại
bad. Your husband is thinking you're
xấu xa đi rồi chồng mình đang nghĩ mình
bad, and now it's increasing to 20 parts bad. Yes, right?
xấu người thì giờ tăng lên thành xấu 20
Because right now I'm bad again,
Ừ đúng chưa tại vì hiện tại tôi lại xấu
understand? But if you know how to
hay rồi hiểu Nhưng mà nếu như mà biết
observe and control your mind and reduce
quán sát bảo trí mà giảm được anh Tâm
your anger, then it's very good,
mình lúc đấy nó rất là hay
you mechanical engineer, you big drunkard. At what time, you
anh cơ khí đại rượu ạ Lúc mấy giờ mình
just need to say, "Hey, Tâm, you're so angry, you're so angry,
chỉ cần nói là cái thằng Tâm Mày đang
and you're going to hit
tức đang tức thế này mà mày phang lại
that guy back, you're going to... ...
ông kia thịt thì tao Mày bớt lại rồi
Yeah, that's
thành 20 phần rồi đúng không Thì nó Ừ
right, it's thinking badly, and if I
đúng rồi nó đang nghĩ xấu mà mình mình
curse at it, it'll just keep doing the same thing. Don't you see that
chửi nó thì nó cũng mình có thấy là lúc
I'm only adding to the problem?
mình chỉ có phải số thêm không Chứ thế
Otherwise, I wouldn't...  The husband also had to say things like, "This is like
em không nếu mà ông chồng cũng phải nói
this, that is like that," people said, "It
cô thế này thế này thế kia người ta bảo
helps me feel less angry," then, "It's a matter of mindset,"
cô thế này đỡ mình tức rồi cái tâm thức
but knowing about karma, if I
rồi nhưng biết về nhân quả là nếu mình
create more karma, I will
tạo thêm nhân quả thì bây giờ mình sẽ bị
suffer losses now. I honestly told her, "
bị thiệt thòi tướng thì mình bảo thật
Hearing him say that made
chị nghe thấy ông nói cũng bực hết cả
me very angry." But Nhung, just let it go, see it, we'll
mình Nhung thôi cứ để chuyện thấy đó là
resolve it later. Everything will be alright. Just
tí rồi giải quyết đâu còn có đó cứ Trình
present the process, present it, it won't be there anymore.
bày quy trình bày đi ra không còn có đó
Respectfully, dear fellow practitioner Yen, I never just talk without doing.
kính thứ quý đạo hữu Yến không nói suông
That's not
bao giờ cái chuyện đó không phải là
something that can't be done. With guidance
những không làm được với những hướng dẫn
for the five types of things, doing them correctly beforehand,
cho các loại ngũ làm đúng trước khiến
without knowing anything about Buddhist teachings, there's no need to
không hề biết đến phật pháp không phải
write anything at all. The two of us argued, we argued, we argued, we argued, we argued, we argued, there were
viết chút nào hai vợ chồng có cãi nhau
many things,
xích mích cái chuyện cũng nhiều chuyện
many times, not just a few,
tính là cũng nhiều lần chứ không phải ít
but the point is that I
lần nhưng mà đình điểm diện tích là cái
rarely remember. But usually, Yen
chuyện mà ít nhớ Nhưng mà thường Yến có
likes to handle things, for example, that day I didn't
thích xử sự ví dụ như là hôm ấy không
know we were arguing, I only remember that
biết là cãi nhau thì nhấn chỉ còn nhớ
today we're definitely not angry
mỗi việc là hôm nay là chắc không bực
from the day before. I
nhau từ hôm trước giờ cái chuyện được
don't remember the things that happened between us, you two talk
nhau thì không nhớ rồi mày vợ chồng nói
a lot. Go home and do it on the
nhiều lắm Đi về làm hôm nào thần Rằm
1st and 15th of the lunar month.  I went home and saw my
mùng 1 về tới nhà thôi thấy là thấy ông
husband. He bought things to offer incense, something I'd
chồng Nó mua đồ đến thắp hương mình từ
never seen him do before. When I got home, I
trước đây chả thấy ông thắp hương bao
bought things to offer
giờ tối về mình cũng mua đồ về thắp
incense too, and when I got home, I saw his face in the
hương thì về đến nhà thì thấy mặt ống
mirror. I asked him, but he wouldn't answer.
nhòm lên rồi Hỏi không thèm trả lời rồi
I asked him again, but he still wouldn't answer. I was so
mình hỏi không trả lời thì cả thế Mình
frustrated. I was about to prepare the offerings, but I didn't
mới đau đầu mới sắp sửa đồ này theo mưa
forbid him from offering incense to our
không không cấm cô không được thắp hương
ancestors. But it's strange, isn't it?
gia tiên được thôi Nhưng mà hay nhỉ đấy
I did
nhỉ Em có thấy các cụ
n't see our ancestors eat the food they offered. He
em không ăn đồ của khiến đâu Đây là anh
offered incense, and after he finished his portion, he
thắp hương xong cứ ăn xong phần đồ của
ate mine. And that's how
anh thì ăn lên phần đồ của em Thế là
I won! He gave me a thumbs-up, my love.
mình thắng cuộc đấy nó ký đầu yêu ạ Đây
Isn't this like saying I shouldn't add to the situation, or adding
có phải là mình không tạo thêm cho mình
more to it?
bớt đợi nữa
Because people's hearts are
anh Bởi vì các yếu tố tâm của người ta
already angry, and if you
là người ta đang tức mình mà mình lại
add a little more, can they handle it? A
cho thêm một ít nữa thì người ta có chịu
person's heart needs to be
nổi không tâm con người là phần phải
soothed, and soothing it with what's right and just right
vuốt ve mà vuốt ve những cái đúng đạo lý
will make them listen to no one
là người ta sẽ phải chịu không nghe ai
else. For example, if I'm a wife and
bên ngoài nữa Ví dụ như mình là vợ mình
people are badmouthing me, isn't that a
bị người ta nói xấu 7 thế có phải là
disadvantage for me? But if my husband listens, it's not a disadvantage. If he
mình bất lợi chưa mà chồng mình nghe coi
likes it, then I
vẫn lại không bất lợi rồi thích thì mình
have to soothe his heart.  The husband's intention is to
phải vuốt ve cái tâm của người chồng để
show people that his
cho người ta thấy rằng là
wife, My Tam, is wonderful, right?
Mỹ Tâm vợ mình tuyệt vời đúng không Thì
Only then can people change their minds. And
người ta mới có thể thay đổi nghĩ được
we're even closer to her.
chứ còn mình lại còn gũi hơn đó mà Thì
People's hearts feel it themselves;
cái tâm của người ta tự tự cảm nhận cái
this feeling doesn't have words or
cảm nhận này nó không có văn từ các quỹ
principles. It's about feeling, okay? Something that
đạo hữu cái cảm nhận này nhé Cái gì đó
makes you comfortable, something that makes you feel
làm cho mình thoải mái mình có cảm nhận
good. This doesn't have words, does
thích thú Cái này nó có lời nói đó không
it? Even if
không có văn từ phải không dù trong đầu
people think well of you, if you
người ta có Nguyễn nghĩ tốt về mình
insult them, they'll feel
nhưng tâm người ta bị mình chửi người ta
uncomfortable and won't think well of you, so how can they
khó chịu người ta có nghĩ tốt được đâu
change? That's why we
mà phải thay đổi nhá Thế cho nên là ở
should say, "We have principles," that we must
đây nên nói mới có quỹ đạo hữu rằng phải
recognize our own hearts. Yen goes
nhận diện ra cái tâm của mình Yến quay
back to the example of seeing her sister-in-law and brother-
trở lại cái ví dụ thấy em dâu và em
in-law talking about her like that.
chồng về nói mình như thế bảo thế À gồm
Actually, it includes those men, but I thought the
thực ra mấy ông chứ còn tôi cứ tưởng các
aunts and uncles were saying good things about me, that's why I was
cô các chú nói tốt về tôi tôi mới Ngạc
surprised. But if they were saying bad things about me,
nhiên chứ còn nếu mà nói xấu về tối có
what's there to be surprised about? Let me
gì mà ngạc nhiên em
tell you everything. These
cho tôi rất kể hết cho ông nghe này Đây
are the aunts and uncles saying this and that and this and that. As for
là cô chú của nói thế này thế này thế
me, the important thing is what you
này thế này tôi thì cơ quan trọng là ông
think of me. Don't comment.
thấy thế nào về tôi không phát biểu đi
I know if it's okay to fix it, is it right?
tôi có biết được biết sửa có được không
Outsiders can't interfere with
chuẩn chưa Bên ngoài không thể động và
my family, right? I don't
gia đình mình được phải không Tôi không
know how outsiders perceive things, but what's
biết bên ngoài ta cảm nhận tối là nhưng
important is how you perceive it. That's what's
quan trọng ông cảm nhận thôi thế nào đấy
important. Naturally, my
là cái quan trọng thế là tự nhiên là ông
husband sees that I live the same way. What's
chồng thấy là mình sống tất cảm giống
important is your assessment. That's what's
rồi đấy quan trọng cái đánh giá của ông
important. If I live like you, it's vulgar. My husband sees that I live with my
tôi quan trọng cái đó tôi sống như ông
sister-in-law, and he
thì tục cái sống bị em chồng mới lại
sees that I live with you. What's your opinion? Now you say you'll let them find a house, but you feel sorry for them, so you don't give it to them. You don't give it, you don't give it to them. As long as you think I'm good, that's enough. You haven't sent
ông thấy tôi tốt là được rồi chưa gửi
a message to soothe people's hearts,
vuốt ve cái tâm của người ta người ta có
but you're
thoải mái không nhưng mà đây thì lại
fighting. And then you've suffered losses, have
chiến đấu luôn Thế mà mình thiệt hại rồi
n't you? So
phải không có bảo hữu thiệt hại cho nên
when you don't know Buddhist teachings, you use
là khi chưa biết phật pháp thì mình lấy
morality to soothe other people's hearts, right?
đạo lý để vuốt ve tâm người khác đúng
That's right. If morality soothes
đậu đấy Đúng đạo đức được vuốt ve cho
others, then that morality and
người khác thì chính cái đạo lý và đạo
morality will make them convinced,
đức đó người ta khiến cho người ta bị
even if they hear something
cho dù người ta có nghe cái điều không
wrong, they'll only listen for a while,
đúng người ta chỉ nghe một thời gian
right? A balance then...  Then
thôi đúng không một cái cân sau đó rồi
people will come back, so we must
người ta lại quay lại cho nên mình phải
clearly understand the elements of our own mind, then we will
hiểu rõ các yếu tố tâm mình thì mình sẽ
clearly understand the elements of other people's minds. If we know
hiểu rõ được yếu tố tâm người mình biết
how to guide our own mind, then we will know
cách dẫn dắt tâm mình thì mình sẽ biết
how to guide other people's minds. Remember
cách dẫn dắt ông người thế em nhớ nhé
this, my friends: Do you need a friend in your mind? When
các quỹ đạo hữu này tâm có cần người bạn
living with your parents, you must consider what your parents
trên ở với bố với mẹ phải xem Tấm bố mẹ
are so that you can become their friend. When
là cái gì để mình trở thành người bạn
living with your spouse, you must understand
được không ở mới vợ với chồng phải viết
what your spouse's mind is so that you can become their
tâm của vợ chồng mình cái gì để trở
friend. In America, you must know
thành người bạn ở Mỹ anh em phải biết
what kind of mind you have so that you can become their
anh em mình có tâm gì để trở thành người
friend. And you yourself must find a
bạn được không Và chính mình phải tìm
friend for your own mind, then the Dharma center will
người bạn cho tâm mình thì đạo tràng sẽ
be a friend to all the Buddhists because
là người bạn cho tất cả các quý phật vì
the Buddhists need to share their thoughts quickly, because they
các quý phật tử cần phải chia sẻ kịp tâm
haven't mastered their minds yet, right? In
mình chưa làm chủ được phải không Những
times of joy, sadness, this, that, you need a
lúc vui lúc buồn lúc thế này lúc thế kia
friend. So the Dharma center
là phải có người bạn cho nên đạo tràng
will be
sẽ là người
your brother, your Buddhist friends will be
Anh của mình các bạn phật tử sẽ là người
your friends. And when it comes to a friend,
bạn của mình còn khi là người bạn như
you accept that friend as someone who
thế nào thì mình chấp nhận bạn đó phải
helps you understand the nature and consequences of a
giúp cho mình biết được về nhiên về quả
limited path, right? Knowing about
có quỹ đạo hữu hạn đúng không biết về
cause and effect allows you to find peace of mind. But
nhân quả thì mình về an tâm được Còn nếu
if you don't know about cause and effect and just follow it...  In
như không biết về nhân quả mà cứ theo lý
life, we will only suffer because there is
đời thì mình sẽ đau khổ thôi Bởi vì nó
no mechanical solution. My dear, let's
không có cách giải quyết cơ khí đầu yêu
go back to the example of the
ạ thì anh quay trở lại cái ví dụ nói là
son bringing home a daughter-in-law who is
anh con trai dẫn về cô con dâu không ra
worthless. If we don't return to the law of cause and effect, how
gì đấy Thế nếu không quay về nhân quả
can we resolve it? If she takes it,
mình có cách giải quyết đâu việc nó lấy
she takes it. Once she's taken it, how can we
thì nó cứ lấy lấy về rồi thì mình làm
fight against her? We lose both our
sao chiến đấu với nhau mất luôn cả cả
son and her. And what about being rich in magnesium?
con trai lẫn Thế còn giàu Magiê nhé
We must return to the element of cause and
chuyên chúng ta phải quay về yếu tố nhân
effect to guide us, and to the
quả để chúng ta làm định hướng còn quay
element of friendship to soothe
về yếu tố của bạn bè để chúng ta làm dịu
our hearts. Here, if we
đi cái tâm của chúng ta nhé đây chúng ta
want to maintain a peaceful mind, we need two things:
muốn giữ gia tâm thì cần hai cái thứ
first, we need friends
nhất là phải có bạn
in the village who know how to practice Buddhism;
ở làng biết tu tập theo Phật pháp thứ
second, we need to follow the principle of cause and effect. With these two things,
hai là phải theo vị trí nhân quả hai cái
we can control our minds and
đó chúng ta sẽ điều phục được tâm mình
help our lives. Let's
giúp cho cuộc sống của mình An bột nhé
gradually reduce the suffering.
giảm dần để những cái nỗi khổ đau cho em
Yen shares with fellow practitioners:
Yến chia sẻ với các quỹ đạo hữu là hãy
find a friend for your
tìm cho tâm mình một người bạn nhé Hãy
heart. Find a friend for your heart, no matter
tìm cho tâm mình một người bạn hết như
how, so that you can be happy. You
thế nào để cho mình được hạnh phúc nhé
have to find it. Look at your whole life
khi phải tìm cho nó đấy Cái cả cuộc đời
now, dear fellow practitioners, sometimes it's
mình bây giờ cơ quý đạo hữu mà xem có
just...  Even fellow practitioners haven't yet identified
khi chính quỹ đạo hữu cũng chưa xác định
who their true friend is, haven't they?
được đâu là người bạn cho tâm mình đâu
Identifying someone they haven't met yet is like letting them go out to
xác định người chưa gặp đâu là cho nó đi
play, right? Throughout their lives, they haven't
chơi đấy đúng không Cả cuộc đời không
found a single friend for their heart.
tìm thấy cho tâm mình nổi một người bạn
From now on, they must find one. Yes, those
từ bây giờ phải tìm nhá phải đấy những
virtuous and knowledgeable people in
cái bậc thiện lành tri thức trong Phật
Buddhism are good friends,
pháp làm bạn lành của mình là người định
guiding them. Take your fellow
hướng cho mình đấy lấy những người bạn
practitioners as a refuge for Mother
đạo làm chỗ nương tựa cho mẹ
A and the Right Dharma of the Buddha. The practice of
A và Lý Chính pháp của Phật Quán trí
cause and effect is the path for you to
nhân quả là con đường cho mình để mình
follow. Remember, those friends will
đi nhé hãy nằm những người bạn kia sẽ
walk with you on that path. Above is a
cùng đi mình trên con đường đó trên là
reminder from Yen to all our fellow practitioners:
Yến nhắc tất cả các quỹ đạo hữu của
when talking to each other, whether happy or
chúng ta khi nói chuyện với nhau khi vui
sad, let's share with
cũng như khi buồn chúng ta chia sẻ với
each other according to the principle of cause and effect so that we can progress.
nhau theo lý nhân quả để cho chúng ta
Remember to give
được tinh tấn nhá Nhớ là phải bố thí
generously; your heart wants to
thật nhiều cái thằng Tâm mình nó muốn về
give and receive. The elements of the heart
muốn cho đi đấy nhá các yếu tố của tâm
are the desire to give, to make
là nó muốn cho đi muốn làm cho người
others happy. That's the element of the
khác được hạnh phúc Đấy là yếu tố của
heart. A husband wants his wife to be happy, does
tao người chồng cũng có muốn cho vợ được
n't he? A wife doesn't want her husband to be happy, does she? It
hạnh phúc không vợ không muốn cho chồng
's the heart that wants to give,
được hạnh phúc không thấy là cái tâm đấy
not just the husband and wife. The heart
chứ chả phải vợ với chồng gì đó tâm mai
also wants to give; there's no other heart.  Is it only a
cũng muốn cho đi không có tâm ai là chỉ
4-day fever, right? If you receive it, then
sốt 4 ngày nhận đúng không Nhận thì bảo
why do you have to be a beggar all day like
sao mình suốt ngày phải trở thành cái kẻ
this? Right, from the heart,
ăn xin thế này đúng không trên cái tâm
it wants to give. Let's always keep our
nó muốn cho đi Mình hãy luôn luôn để cái
hearts striving to give, and happiness will come naturally. Okay, okay?
tâm nỗ lực cho đi nó sẽ tự hạnh phúc nó
After eating, my fellow practitioners and I,
sẽ tự à
in our family, have happy and sad moments. The
trong gia đình có chuyện vui chuyện buồn
Dharma comes together, right? Then, encouraging
Đạo chữ cùng đến đúng không Rồi sách tấn
each other, isn't that giving? When
nhau có phải là cho đi không trên khi mà
this person, I'll encourage them once,
Cái người này mình sẽ tấn một lần hai
twice, three times, and if it doesn't work, it's because of their karma. With
lần ba lần chưa được mà do nghiệp của
perseverance, it will really work. Each
người ta kiên trì mà sẽ thật nhé tôi mỗi
time I encourage someone, it's just giving, right? There's nothing to it.
lần sách tấn là một lần cho đi thôi phải
Give. Give
không có gì đâu Cho đi Cho đi cái quan
care, give sharing, give
tâm cho đi cái chia sẻ cho đi cái tâm
your loving heart. That's good, right? Yes, yes.
yêu thương của mình Thế là tốt nhá
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]